all right welcome back we are here with
John clippinger and we will be
discussing active inference biofirm
homeostatic agents for Biore Regional
and regenerative Finance so thank you
John looking forward to this
presentation and discussion and
more Daniel thank you so much for doing
this and hosting this uh it's been a
great set of sessions it really has has
been very informative and this is a
followup on a a session that we had
yesterday on basically um what active
inference agents and why they're
important and uh and looking at them in
an application and in this case in this
session we were going to look at active
inference agents uh in terms of a
concept called biofirm uh as a
homeostatic agent support Biore Regional
regenerative Finance we're really
looking at that the taking the thinking
behind active inference agents and
applying it to a new notion of the firm
that's inherently biomedic and and what
I wanted with these series of slides is
to sort of set up the conversation and
the discussion that we're going to have
later with Andrew and Daniel on the
providing an in-depth look at at biof
firms as a homeostatic agent that is
capable of interacting with the
environment in a way that preserves it
and pres preserves itself in the
environment um so so what I'd like to
begin with is sort of this a premise
I've been involved in uh looking at
regenerative finance and issues around
climate change for at least the last 10
years and I think there's a growing
consensus that we need a new kind of
science-based Economy based an enhancing
life in nature and quality you really
need to to think about what are the
economic incentives uh to make a
transition to an economy that values the
preservation of life and nature rather
than the extraction or destruction of
it and what we don't need is what we've
we're we're now feeling the the
consequences of it and that's the
commodification of nature in people
turning them into objects and assets
that can be bought and sold and trade
without any discrimination between sort
of what kind of asset we're talking
about were you talking about something
that is is coal as water as life the
biosphere they're all assets
uh they can all be priced and they all
can be traded um and so you just have
problem of total fungibility when
actually some things are essential for
existence and they exist in relationship
to other things to be preserved as
living things um and and the other
problem we're seeing it experiencing it
widespread just today sort of the
unbounded sort of concentration of of of
wealth and power so we have a system
that works towards monopolies and the
concentration of wealth and privilege
and and this of course has created
enormous pressures not only sort of on
the the ecology but on the whole society
itself and you have this notion of
maximizing individual utility so
everything is about Freedom the
individuals in atomic agent independent
of the context in which they live and
their impact upon others not just other
people but their other species the whole
environment um and so we have extracted
metrics that with negative externality
so so know there's you can create quote
economic returns but what you're doing
is creating a negative externality would
be pollution or it be uh air pollution
destruction of species or habitat this
is not reflected in the price and then
it's left to some other party to a
public good party to clean up the mess
but this is they're not able to clean up
the mess fast enough than it's being
created so we have a sort of a zero sum
win or take incentive structure and we
have a lack of transparency and
accountability so there's no sense of of
collective purpose so th this is is
really forc people to rethink what an
economy should be uh and and what it
would be to have biomatic firms an
economy something that that actually
worked in concept with nature not
against nature so first thing is
important is not to have any negative
externalities this idea that that you
you can offset the cost of something is
going to be picked up by other parties
since their carbon credits and offsets
are really an attempt a failed attempt
to deal with negative
externalities and we we need to get
where we need to have nonzero sum
incentives in other words incentivize
the collaboration and cooperation of
parties to take Joint outcomes rather
than maximizing utility for a single
individual and we need to have a new way
of recognizing that value is created in
in a really scientific incredible sense
that Val is recognized when value is
recognized through a bio capacity and
diversity and resilience have that be a
notion of value not just to something
that maximizes a price Arbitrage but
actually creates new kind of value the
other important thing I think is is
coming into focus is this idea of agency
um and this is sort of A New Concept
that thinks that ah nature should have
agency we should have an agency and we
should have agency of of of thinking of
nature is being given the capacity to be
itself and species to be itself and
people to be themselves and not have
that be restricted and with that I think
we comes the notion of what we call sort
of homeostatic fungibility in other
words how something is is value of that
realized is in relation to keeping other
things Al life if you look at the the
human body it's like you can't maximize
the utility of the heart against the
brain or the lungs they all exist
together so how you allocate resources
in the body is really maintaining the
balances between those different kinds
of organs and that's true of Nature and
that's true of
organizations what we need also is a
sort of scale-free and domainfree
metrics that's scientific and adaptable
so we really need to have the scientific
process be a fundamental organizing
principle by how we recognize and and
and and and and exchange value um and
this means having something that's
really is transparent
explainable you can't have something
that's a black box that's not opaque
that you don't know where it comes from
you don't know how to trust it you don't
know how to derive it it really needs to
be something that's transparent and so
we've seen people talk about the
blockchain and things like that but it's
more than just a blockchain it's a whole
set of methods being able to see how
something is derived and be able to
replicate that and then the idea of
scalable Learning Systems should learn
and they should improve over time
markets don't necessar do that they just
they actually they they they they have
clear a market around a price and then
they start again there's no memory
there's no learning how to do something
better for adaptation as as a people and
in the planet we need to learn we need
to learn improve upon ourselves and that
should be part of our whole economy not
something that's tangental to it and
finally the whole idea of governance
there's governance should not be
something apply after the fact or top
down it should really be embedded in the
whole system of itself and so this's
been a lot of talk about decentralized
governance and decentralized system
decentralized autonomous
organizations but a lot of that is just
talk they're not really fully autonomous
and not fully decentralized but how do
you really realize that that
vision and these these ideas have really
sort of were first I think articulated
and
recognized um by The Economist uh elanar
a who got a Nobel Prize for her work um
on the governance of econom and she was
the first woman Economist to do that and
and I'd worked with elener when I was at
the Harvard the burkman center and
looking and and trying to get thinking
about a digital common sent it was too
early but here are some of the central
principles that she had and this is back
then when the technology was not very
developed but she developed her thinking
based upon how indigenous people managed
resources their common resources and
that would be their their their their
forestry the Fisheries the things that
they've done for thousands of years and
they're able to keep them in balance and
keep their lifestyle in Balance through
that and here were some principles she
extracted from that so was clearly
defined boundaries um and you needed to
have a a common po resource where people
recognize as a common po resources you
have to have it congruent with local
conditions and I think be that in other
words you have to recognize each little
bio region had its own
PE uh constraints and and and issues
that you needed to recognize and you had
to have ways of people could make
Collective choices among up Commons how
bring people together they couldn't be
anonymous one they really had to be they
had to know each other and they be
accountable to one another and you had
monitoring process you had to monitor it
and be able to see where you were and
then if something goes wrong you have
what she called graduated sanctions
which means it was you you the punish
was was commensurate with the degree of
the violation but you really didn't want
to have a highly punitive system that
its own negative results and you had
various mechanisms for re resolving
conflict um and then I think the the the
idea one of the things she her concerns
with particularly with indigenous people
is that the legitimacy of those
organizations were recognized by the
larger nation state that that that they
had some genuine sovereignty and
integrity and finally this whole idea of
nested Enterprises so recognizing it
wasn't a strict hierarchy there was
things that dynamically interacted at
different scales and these were ideas
that were sort of more metaphors at the
time they were aspirational metaphors
was very hard to realize in any kind of
operational form and she went on to talk
about later work in social ecological
systems and recognized the biophysical
and the social factors how they all work
together and V and how you look across
different spatial temporal scales and
different hierarchies how they're linked
um and she was always starting to think
about what were the dynamic complex
systems that can characterize by a
adaptation if you're going to have
governance but where there really wasn't
a mechanism there for for how to realize
those
ideas now there's another more recent
development uh is actually it's called
tanu that was started by a friend of
mine um name is jonath lagard is in
Africa and they're doing this in Rwanda
and they're doing it with all kinds of
species
are they starting out with the gorillas
or W but the idea is is that animals
species contribute to the environment
and they should be paid for the value
that they created so how do you do that
you're giving agency not only to the
animal but to the to the habitat in this
case in Rwanda they want to give not
only agency to say gorillas Rwanda
gorillas but they also they want to give
agency to a rivers in in certain bio
regions and by agency it mean the the
fact that they these things is staying
alive can be valued for their capacity
to stay alive and create a habitat that
creates a a successful and and resilient
environment um and so what is this is a
quote from uh their their literature
their website which I recommend you
taking a look at and exists with the
belie that for these species leave they
must actively participate in the economy
so how do you create a new economy that
includes living things and and and how
do you how do you recognize that
value another approach is something
that's come from regen networks which
has been working on this for a number of
years and I've worked with them and
they're talking about creating
ecological
institutions and again it's like what is
an institution an institution in in the
classic sense is separation of people
from a set a set of principles like the
rule of law you say well here's an
institution and it's set up to do these
things and people to perform certain
roles in an
institution um but the problem with
institutions is that they're run by
people people get corrupted and they
institutions don't work in this case
what they're trying to do is develop a
constitution for they call an ecological
subject and again is giving agency and
recognition to Nature um and then they
have a number of of of methods by which
to to govern that and put in a ledger
create some token system Region's been
doing this kind of work for quite a
while all part of a common effort
another effort is is something called a
bi Regional Hub and this will be my last
example before making the transition um
but the the the idea of a b Regional Hub
is that to pull together different
parties in a particular geospatial
location and be able to give them a a a
set of finance and incentives by which
they can act to actually create the bio
capacity of that particular GE region
and so it's really working with core
communities that that are committed to
actually en enhancing a could be a river
a river system it could be the one of
there they're looking at in Northeast uh
bio region is the Connecticut River how
can you bring it back to where it was
with abundance when they had full salmon
they had was a very rich ecological
system but there are other things in
terms of land owners and being able to
give them the incentives to rewi their
property and actually make a living on
that and create an economy an exchange
of value in such a way that makes it
robust and resilient um and so they're
working with different kinds of
investors and social impact investors in
order to make this kind of happen so
this is part of a larger collection of
people are trying to do these things now
what we're going to say what I and this
is a very cred I apologize for the the
verbiage here but the we're and and what
you're going to hear in this the
subsequent discussion is this idea of a
biofirm is a bio which is is a firm that
is based upon homeostatic principles and
it really I think addresses the many
issues both operational and aspirational
that you see in the whole bof Finance
movement and and and to to to run
through this fairly quickly but you're
going to find Andrew and Daniel going to
talk about these things in detail with
examples is that it's first principles
based it's grinded in scientific method
basing in statistics and markup blankets
in other words you drill down to it and
you really understand it rigorously as a
science you can understand where what
it's based upon and why how things work
in a principled way it's also
computationally tractable at scales and
and with free metrics for doing uh the
whole kind of reporting uh and and uh
that you you have this required
environmental reporting they call mrvs
um sort of uh and so do you have a
method by which you can make statements
and claims about the state of the
environment that is scales that scales
and and and can be used for cross
comparisons it's also going to be its
open source so the bar form is like a
kernel think of it as a Linux kernel for
a new kind of organizational structure
can then generate a new kind of economy
that's Biomet biometrically based
another key component is if we're going
to scale our capacity to deal with
nature it's going to be a lot is going
to have to be automated it's there's so
many tasks involved in different parts
of the world that you have different
skill sets how do you how do you
automate some very complex things in a
in a way that can be trusted and
generate metrics that other people are
willing to accept this has been a big
problem in climate change and this is
where the the an extraordinary
automation of cognitive tasks through
through large language models
Transformers and agent architecture
allows for an automation of many many of
the tasks of collecting and analyzing
the data and learning from the data this
is very significant um and then you can
create you have the capacity to have
create networks of Agents working
together and create a system exchange so
that's a Natural Evolution that's
happening into edge-based Computing that
you can have Computing on the edge you
can security The Edge that's another
phenomena and then I think you know the
the idea of polycentric government this
not is made of that but what does that
really mean well really means if you
look at agents that are self-organizing
agents and dynamically relating to one
another on the basis of the free energy
principle these other principles you
have the effect of of of a polycentric
governance um and you also have the
ability to formally give agency to
Nature to different species to different
peoples to different kind of
competencies so that is the whole nature
as to say of of an agentic architecture
um and then I think you you have a
principal means of interfacing between a
biometric economy and the the the
current economy that's going to be
really important so you can't just live
in your own little world you're going to
have to interchange with the the Fiat
economy of the world in such a way that
actually protects and and establishes
the value of a biometric economy finally
I think it provides a a a principal
basis for valuing nature-based
currencies and assets that we we can
discu a little bit in the time to come
so that that is that's basically uh my
my comments I think that I like to end
is said let's make it real that we're
actually I think you'll see in the
following discussions we're at a point
where I think the technology is getting
sufficiently mature to actually engage
in developing use cases of this and
bring it to scale so with that I I'll
hand it over to uh Andrew thank you
great thanks
John um quick mention to Daniel uh John
and I had a a really nice conversation
prior to this if it's possible uh I
might actually start my talk now uh and
then yeah perfect I was hoping that
would be the case and then that way John
and I can also have a little bit of back
and forth potentially during the course
uh and obviously Daniel you've had so
such a big hand in the development so
anytime you know yeah would like to
chime in please feel free
great um all right so my original plan
talk for today was entitled uh let me
get rid of this guy uh active inference
is a framework for social science-based
uh modeling and
okay
um something happened on the way to the
Symposium yeah exactly uh huge updates
uh I I want to just give a little bit of
context uh for some time now I've uh you
know I personally gave a talk a couple
of months ago a three point a three and
a half hour Workshop basically at a
International Conference for
computational social sciences uh hold at
held at University of Pennsylvania uh
July 17th this year and uh what what I
was trying to do was basically teach uh
computational social scientists that
means economists sociologists political
scientists and so on who are very Savvy
with computers essentially um how we
might be able to employ active inference
uh in agent-based modeling which is
already you know a decades old at this
point uh method of Designing uh uh
basically simula
of Agents inside of environments where
agents might be you know human beings
and an environment might be you know a
market system or or some other kind of
environment that you know uh humans find
themselves in where you can you know you
can play out simulations test things and
so on I want to introduce that to
computational social scientists and I
think more broadly what's what's great
is that this Symposium now gives me the
opportunity to kind of flip it to where
I can kind of bring some of what
computation social science does to other
active inference researchers um but to
stay on with the
biofirm uh I really wanted to again as
Daniel said something happened on the
way to the Symposium uh I've had these
conversations with with John since uh
since I did that conference and uh I
have a lot of kind of strong intuition
that a lot of what he's been describing
is is a really wonderful sort of
direction for future work in both agent
based modeling but also applications of
that kind of in the real world um I mean
we're always operating under conditions
of you know uncertainty and and trying
to figure out kind of what to do in very
adaptive ways where our environment is
is constantly changing uh from you know
implementation of computers social
networks uh we have climate change we
have uh the typical booms and busts of
our economic systems and so on so um so
I'll I'll start here but I just want it
to be known like there have been a lot
of heavy revisions to this with a lot of
development we've made on the biofirm D
featuring biofirm uh so again I'm Andrew
pase uh I my day job I work as a data
analyst scientist engineer always many
roles to fill uh and so uh I I bring a
lot of those kind of skills with me to
active inference and how I view things
like developing um kind of applications
uh for specific use cases and things
like that I think there can be a lot of
Rich uh interdisciplinary dialogue
between you know different fields and
that includes the kinds of things I do
on a day-to-day basis versus uh my
interest in active inference which has
been going for the past few years now so
I've I've been a an intern and I I
suppose I'm feeling much more like a
like a full-time uh kind of affiliate of
the institute at this point I've been
teaching the the text group um uh with
Daniel co- facilitating that I've been
involved in various projects uh and so
and then now this kind of partnership
with with first principles first and
what uh Dr Cliff and jur is trying to
accomplish and and developing the
biofirm so I just want to put uh you
know on this title slide here these are
actually links to you know if you would
like to get involved with the active
inference Institute with uh check out
all the kinds of things that are being
put out by first principles first and
also I just want it to be known like you
can come back to these slides as needed
as well as any of the other kind of
learning materials I've been produced
saying whether it be for the the
conference that I did a couple months
ago including on the code uh how to
actually create active inference uh
Agents from scratch uh moving up to
multi-agent simulations and so on I also
did a talk with the Institute recently
that kind of walks through some of the
some of the code so
um the the new outline for this talk
we're going to touch again on agent
based modeling which we already talked
about yesterday uh a little bit in h the
first Workshop so I'm we're going to
kind of skim through that a little bit
but I W to I want to put some special
attention upon the aspect that uh of
Agia based modeling referring to what
are called micro assumptions about
Behavior Point Blank if we're going to
simulate humans we have to include
certain assumptions uh about how we
think humans behave if we're going to
simulate them in an environment right
otherwise we just we we can create a
list of humans they do nothing until we
give them some kind of rules or
behavioral you know Dynamics or
something along those lines so those are
essential uh for for setting up agent
based modeling and then uh and then
we'll shift over into active inference
we'll look at the PDP as a kind of
Exemplar model talk about some agent
multi-agent examples just to give a
sense of what kind of work be done in
this area many people watching this now
who who are already involved with active
inference there'll be some aspects of
this that are you know might come off as
a little repetitive but I just I don't
want to I I I want to stick to the the
textbooks so to speak right I want to
kind of keep this grounded in a sense
that you know folks who know about
active inference don't know about active
inference have some vague interest in
active inference in this in between area
like can catch on to the material here
um next we'll go into this question are
llms agents uh there's a lot of exciting
work being done with llms uh they're
showing incredibly uh you know exciting
and surprising uh you know sophisticated
reasoning uh skills and capacities for
dealing with natural language that said
um you know and it's already been said
so many times in the other talks given
in you know during the Symposium but
it's worth repeating like they have
limits
there are issues and I and I've been
doing some work on thinking through how
do llms relate to things like cognitive
theories what how does an llm think or
how how does that work really so that we
can really grasp if we want to
incorporate llms into say agent based
modeling software applications or
otherwise let's let's come to terms with
like the reality of what they are before
assuming too much about what they are or
what they're capable of and furthermore
how we might to integrate them into kind
of more grounded means doing agent-based
modeling such is working with actual
agents the quick answer to our llms
agents agents are they agents no that
that's the quick answer they they are
not uh that's what I will claim and then
we'll move on to the biofirm which
frankly will take up the majority of the
rest of the talk uh from there so uh
what is agent-based modeling uh as
already stated we have agents more
specifically uh you know it's a
programmed entity it could be a person a
living organism it could be
representative of an entire institution
uh or otherwise uh and basically
programmatically it receives
observations from its environment and
then it returns actions back into its
environment for example an agent could
be a person an investor and then uh with
the environment uh the the environment
could be an artificial or real uh system
that elicits observations agents and
then receives the agents actions uh
those actions then impact the
environment itself in turn for example
the environment could be a stock market
so we see that there's this reciprocal
relationship between the two things an
agent or environment's action is an
environment or agents observation so the
agent sees a price signal from the
environment they make a purchase uh next
morning prices have adjusted given that
agent maybe other agents purchases you
see so there's this kind of back and
forth in a loop uh you know a certain
time interval such as in time steps or
we could imagine them in days like on
day one this happened day two this
happened an active inference the agent
environment's respective Markov blankets
which kind of Define what it is to be
that entity whether it be the agent or
what it means to be that environment
including all the the the structure uh
the characteristics you know if if it's
a person that maybe it includes things
like their goals or or their um uh what
it means to maintain homeostasis so an
individual has a you know blood and
oxygen flows in their body you know what
does it mean to be that entity so from
there we simulate them we play out the
agent environment Dynamics over time
again as I said in time steps some other
kind of interval and uh and in active
inference we often use the phrase action
perception Loop you know it's like a you
do something then you perceive the
outcome you elicit your next action you
know receive the outcome and then you
know arguably this happens at a very
rapid Pace in actual human beings right
this is goes beyond just time step one
or two or looking you we measure this in
in in Nan seconds or otherwise so core
guidelines setting up agent based models
we want to make realistic yet simplest
possible agents and environments that
has to do with you know
uh generalizability if you make
something that's so unique to a
particular situation it might not
generalize well uh you know so if you
want to make an agent agent based model
of say uh you know agents taking care of
a natural environment if you make the
agents way too specific to that
environment to where they you know if
you if you want to set up this
agent-based model get insights into what
you can do in reality you want to make
sure that what you test in the model can
actually be carried out in reality can't
be too specific it can't be off course
um robustness simply small changes don't
dramatically change results uh so you
know if you fine-tune something too much
such that you know the the results of
the um experiment end up being
dramatically different and suddenly once
again we have that generalizability
problem
reproducibility everyone knows
reproducibility problems exist in modern
science we need to document and publish
uh you know our code make it available
to other people so they can understand
it recreate the results Etc and finally
usefulness which is simply why do this
you know if we can't if we can't get any
kind of additional useful insights out
of setting up these rather complex
computer models and and programs um you
know why do it and so it's it's worth
having that in mind you know not not all
models are right uh but but some models
can be useful right in the statis and
George Box's words then um
purpose so we do agent based modeling in
order to predict outcomes we could try
and extrapolate from the present uh we
can entertain different kinds of
hypothetical scenarios design new
policies and and have them play out over
the course of the simulation to see what
the outcome is and then we can also look
at Collective outcomes of aggregated
individual behaviors if all uh you know
stock investors in my simulation
All Began investing in this particular
stock like what happens by the next day
do we end up with some kind of bubble
and then bust kind of situation like
what what occurs you know that kind of
thinking and then over the past couple
decades and this is really what I want
to highlight a couple months ago and
what I would like to highlight now again
and I think it's especially relevant for
anyone wanting to do agent based
modeling and especially folks who are
interested in active inference there's
been a cognitive turn uh you know a lot
of these traditional agent based models
you know they're very you know very
interesting a lot of thought has has has
been put into them but their agents tend
to be very simplistic um in part because
you know 40 years ago we were working
with uh you know much more at this point
archaic uh computers and computer
architectures and and devices that
simply could not run uh simulations that
involve many interacting agents who all
have highly sophisticated you know
Behavior furthermore it's called a
cognitive turn not a complexity turn but
a cognitive turn in the sense that we're
looking at actually more closely
approximating human behavior so that
means actually looking at other fields
ranging from you know Neuroscience
cognition psychology social sciences I
means looking at uh you know cybernetics
uh biology you know trying to open up
the the discourse and the dialogues over
how can we more better approximate human
behavior so there's some common
characteristics for these calls to
cognitive agents that includes like
having inter you know agents have
beliefs um they update their beliefs
based upon what they see they have to
infer what to do in a sense that they're
more autonomous they they kind of make
their own decisions traditional
agent-based modeling it's like well if
if if if the agent sees X then they do y
otherwise they do Z and these highly
simplistic you know programmatic rules
that you know the program you know I
program them that way so I already know
that they're going to do that uh
whenever it comes to agent based
modeling with cognitive agents I don't
necessarily know exactly what they're
going to do they kind of make their own
decisions right they have the
architecture for that and then also
reinforcement learning which is kind of
a you know adjacent or subfield uh in
some ways of like machine learning data
science you know a lot of these kind of
state-of-the-art but still rather
standardized at this point ways of doing
modern data uh you know processing and
analytics and and predictions and
forecasting uh reinforcement learning is
the way of doing that where you actually
have an agent all right so um so that's
been kind of one of the main ways people
are trying to to continue this cognitive
turn and agent based
modeling now micro assumptions there a
lot of information for a single slide so
you know it'll be over soon but I I
really just wanted to give uh um you
know kind of a picture of there there is
so much research that's been done so
many more kind of dialogues between
fields that that can occur uh here now
um like when thinking about how to make
cognitive agents what makes sense you
know what what what's realistic but what
also balances complexity and accuracy
keeps things simple enough to where the
agent-based model can actually be useful
so there's been a lot of criticism at
this point centuries criticism of this
kind of neoclassical tradition classical
than neoclassical tradition Adam
smithian kind of tradition uh that tends
to paint humans as utility maximizers
you know it's often criticized because
it's too simplistic it reduces people to
being uh greedy or immoral you know as
if they're just going after you know
profit without any concern for uh any
other you know condition or needs or
wants or you know um so kind of
selfishness right without any form of Al
altruism or S of community um some
people point to Economist Lionel Robbins
you know kind of a classic in the field
uh who claim that unlimited wants scarce
resources that is the fundamental
economic problem yet this assumption I
think this gets overlooked I also
criticize the utility maximizer
assumption but I I want people to be
aware that this this leads to a a really
useful tool
which is for agent based modeling you
can severely reduce computational costs
for putting together agent based models
if you just have a bunch of agents who
are trying to act to maximize a singular
value there's not a lot of complexity
there you can you can run those
equations quite quickly right and then
that also assumes that the main thing in
your environment is the singular value
that is utility or a stand in might be
uh you know money or or some general
notion of liquidity and so
since then we've had so many other ways
of looking at Human Behavior Uh
behavioral economics and finance
psychology cognitive science social
theory you know humans aren't just
trying to maximize utility they're
they're they're speculative they don't
have fixed preferences they actually
look at one another's decision makings
you know this goes back to you know John
Mayor KES we had h himman p Minsky who
looked at uh you know Market crashes we
have Robert J Schiller who's still life
today in writing on narrative economics
the idea that you know ideas have an
impact on how we interact with our
economy and how how we behave um there's
conans thinking fast and slow like
sometimes we just rely upon hor istics
or maybe we do it a lot of the time you
know it's quicker it's it just um it it
mitigates having to put a lot of thought
into things where we just kind of want
to get something done even though it's
not necessarily maximizing utility um
there's star and Stein's nudge it's like
sometimes yeah you do just go with the
default option some people whenever a
website asks them like do you accept all
the cookies they will click yes quickly
just because they want the thing off
their screen right um so and then we
have social emulation Amis convergence
ideology all these theories um you know
what is what is money it brings up the
question of what is utility what is
money currency actually isn't just a
means of exchange it's not just you can
also a store of value as its own value
changes to to you know TR try and do
kind of economic transfers to make sure
that you get higher value out of
whatever form of currency you're holding
uh it's also a social institution though
it's much broader right so be having
access to money as many of us know
allows you to be uh first you have
access to a variety of Commodities
assuming you're in a market economy
where many things are fungible and
tradable in that way and then we also
have social belonging it's very
difficult to maintain yourself in a
society where you have no money right so
there a it's a whole dimension that that
is lost we just look at something like
maximizing utility uh you know I've put
a mention of Lou alus which is a much
more kind of critical theory approach
but it looks that the impact of state
law uh you know different forms of
coercion upon people to to act and
behave in particular ways that go beyond
just their ability to to try and
maximize their own profit the pragmatism
people up ate their beliefs they're
forward-looking they don't maintain the
same preferences and ideas and rules uh
you know throughout history you know
they change they have their own
circumstances and so there's a kind of
pragmatic uh approach to life Carl pan
economic activity is embedded in society
uh meaning that a lot of the AC economic
activities that we have you know they
themselves are predicated upon our
ability to trust one another work with
one another and all these other kind of
things where whenever that trust is
harmed it can dramatically change how
that economic activity plays out and
then we have Neuroscience biology
physics and that you can see how we're
moving more in the active inference
Direction now but you know that we have
these are predominant theories now in
neural science the idea of predictive
processing that you know that one comes
to a situation with their prior beliefs
and they they they can be updated in the
sense of the the Basi and brain offis a
kind of way of mathematizing that that
process we also have and this is quite
old now but it's still still stands as a
role like heian learning or associative
learning you know so someone who
Associates money with being something
bad very well might not you know have
such a drive for money versus relative
to other things um and then homeostasis
allostasis allostasis being planning for
homeostasis or homeostasis in the future
these are obvious things for us that we
deal with on the day-to-day we need to
to fulfill our needs uh physiological
needs neurobiological needs uh
unconscious processes in the brain you
know that goes beyond being able to say
that every single thing that we do is
necessarily conscious or deliberate
right I I'm not actively trying to think
about how to regulate my blood or oxygen
flow right now uh we also take
preventative actions you know we do
things that might be a cost right now
but they change you know the impact of
whatever happens in the future for us uh
we are forward looking in in various
ways and we do often rely upon habits as
needed uh to fulfill our needs habits
allow us to do things without having to
put in too much expenditure mental
expenditure you know metabolic
expenditure to ensure that our needs are
going to continuously be fulfilled and
cybernetics embedded cognition uh you
know PE this is the idea that behavior
and even intelligence arise from
interactions between brain body and
environment which kind of overcomes some
of these uh ideas you classical ideas of
a cognition mainly being uh outside in
where you just kind of look at what's
around you and then you you take that in
as a passive Observer um instead we're
actually always in communication with
what's around us and Mortal computation
in the sense of we can move in the
direction of you know if we want to do
something like cognitive modeling then
we're looking more at uh you know
actually trying to mirror these kinds of
processes they're much more realistic
collabor ation imitation computational
Neuroscience Psychiatry and modeling
modeling internal Dynamics in form of
you know time series neuroimaging data
uh you know applying different kinds of
techniques like causal inference to see
how one factor impacts another one
variable impacts another um actually
trying to find correlations between
internal neuronal Dynamics with actual
behaviors that occur uh you know so so
for example sticking you know kind of
electrophysiological like electrodes on
you know a mouse and a in a tze to see
like okay what kinds of neuronal
Dynamics correlate with you know the rat
choosing to go left to find the reward
uh you know find the cheese or otherwise
and then and then taking that and trying
to move in the direction of you know
creating an agent who who basically is
fit to the behavior of that that Miler
rat in the team ma right that's a
classic kind of example that's in active
inference and we also have the
hamiltonian principle of least action
much more in the realm of physics um and
it's it deserves a whole you know slide
or 10 you know on its own but the the
main idea figuratively is you know the
idea of uh something occurring uh based
on following whatever the easiest path
is from one state to to another so a lot
of these things the idea of you know
social homeostasis
uh you know relying upon horis sixs
versus planning and forward-looking
versus dealing with whatever's going on
in the moment just because you need to
figure out what to do now even though
it's not something you plan for all
these kind of aspects start to come
together I argue an active inference uh
so it's kind of like you know is this
should we be considering something like
comomo economic is revised you know
again liquidity is the means for all
Commodities at least in our market
economy at least assum assuming
fungibility of things that liquidity can
get you many many things in a certain
way I almost want to dial it back on
saying it's immoral to want liquidity uh
it allows you to fulfill your needs
again in a market economy by seeking out
Necessities for your own homeostasis or
allostasis you know physiological relief
or otherwise even then even as your bank
account increases that doesn't
necessarily mean you're going to have
your social needs met kinship or
familial needs met physical health uh
you know if if a doctor tells me after
I've suffered some kind of injury that I
actually need to do stretches now in
order to make sure that my arm will move
going forward in the way that I need it
to it doesn't matter how large my bank
account is I'm still going to have to do
those stretches right um so there this a
simplistic example but all of this is to
say uh you know for agent based modeling
rather than thinking of utility
especially utility in some vague
abstract sense of you know is it money
is it liquidity is it something else
there could be a shift to a kind of
alternative uh you know what is
essentially a virtually textually
Universal value computed by the brain
which can Encompass not just to drive to
liquidity but other aspects and means of
Life simple as possible yet no simpler
and then it itself becomes a simplified
recordable rip metric for measuring
one's capacity for current and future
survival uh and so that you know enter
the energy principle which is one of the
central principles of active inference
uh here we're minimizing quantifiable
uncertainty uh you know that by
minimizing this it allows us to achieve
our goals fulfill our needs we learn we
actually change our minds you know we
learn new information we are not fixed
beings who you know are are are kind of
one-dimensional we update our beliefs
and uh free energy is a proxy for uh
uncertainty or surprise you know it's
it's computed quite easily uh you know
because it's a it's a variational
quantity there's a approximate
computation which you know in in
physical living beings that keeps our
metabolic costs low uh and and for
agent-based modeling that also means
keeping computational costs low and so
it still kind of fits you know that the
the the usefulness of what utility was
for agent based modeling I think that
free energy can instead be the new kind
of metric that we're looking at um and
you know I included this kind of a you
know fun fact that there was a nice talk
given uh not too long ago with active
inference uh Institute uh you know some
folks who do neuromorphic Computing just
reminded us like despite how many
calories their bodies use on the day
today the brain only requires roughly
four bananas worth of calories despite
the fact that it makes 10 to the 15 uh
calculations per second it's just a
reminder of like this this variational
aspect
being able to do quicker approximations
and then um you know we talk a lot about
free energy but I just I really you know
in the in the kind of funniest kind of
way I just uh have always been
fascinated by this equation uh this is
you know textbook equation uh from
active inference but you know so G is
our expected free energy related to
deliberative planning goal attainment
information seeking conditioned on our
homeostatic preferences right so we plan
for things to care of ourselves to to
accomplish things we need to F is
variational free energy another quantity
Where We balance the complexity and
accuracy of how do we deal with the
moment then we can think of this as like
you know say you're camping in the woods
and suddenly there's a bear it's like
well you didn't plan for that uh and you
didn't expect that and coming up against
a potentially dangerous bear is probably
very much against your preferences for
maintaining your homeostasis in this
case your sense of physical safety so
you have to deal with that and then e uh
you know those are your habits your
horis so so what I'm saying is that I
just I I'm particularly appreciate that
we we have a quantifiable way you know
here of trying to decide what uh you
know what it is that determines
someone's actual Behavior you know that
the posterior beliefs High meaning what
policy or action should I take right uh
all of that is kind of all all these
different considerations habits
deliberative planning momentto moment
planning all these things are are
involved in that so it's just it's kind
of it's it's an attempt at from my
perspective like we're actually
combining many of these inter
disciplinary perspectives into a single
equation there and so active inference I
think I I I appreciate this attempt to
try and do this kind of mapping of you
know sub you know neurobiological
substrates to actually interpretable
cognitive theory regarding what is a
habit how does that you know what what
composes that in the brain what are
goals what is planning what is action
and then from there moving on to uh you
know these kind of Exemplar uh initial
active inference uh models which
themselves are highly relatable to to
reinforcement learning so it's all to
make the case that active inference I
think it draws connections and kind of
builds Bridges between all of these uh
you know these other disciplines in a
way that that is very rich and it's not
so uh exclusive right it doesn't it
doesn't stop conversations it starts
them so and then I also wanted to show
like here is just a quick list of some
multi-agent simulations with active
inference that I think you know heavily
relates it is agent-based modeling you
can open the a textbook from a couple
years ago agent-based modeling is there
you know it's this isn't foreign to to
active inference but I just I hope those
in the agian based modeling Community
can start to see how strong these
relationships are with active inference
so um epistemic communities under active
inference this this uh paper was um you
know recreating agents who hold their
own opinions uh about things and they're
they're in social networks so you can
study how they share beliefs with one
another and yet given you know a lot of
these kind of formal principles and
active inference seeing how that plays
out we can actually see what the kinds
of dynamics that we start to see on
Twitter and other social networks where
you know opinion polarization begins to
happen depending on uh how you know how
the network is set up in the first place
so um you know it's just it's very
interesting we also have active INF for
ants this is much much more kind of a
biological or Zoological example uh you
know where there're ants in a colony who
who uh have to adjust to changing
context such as uh changing food
locations and they leave one another
pheromones so they can um actually
follow one another's Trails so to speak
to find the food and come back um and
then this is very recent but uh we had
another talk earlier today but the um
this paper with Connor Hines who is one
of the developers of pmdp which we'll be
seeing shortly uh he and you know frisen
and others are are developing further
tools for doing active inference and
this kind of gets at the question of
like nestedness and and looking at how
um you know you have a bunch of
individual agents what where are the
cases where their Collective Behavior
actually you could fit that behavior
back to the individual parameters that
each of the individual agents hold um
and then again with social science like
looking at agents who have distinct
roles uh such as leader and follower
where or it could be you know you could
apply this logic to many other
situations the ideas just looking at how
agents to have their own distinct uh you
know uh uh available actions and beliefs
nonetheless uh you know whenever they're
kind they can kind of synchronize in
their capacity to fulfill uh you know a
goal that they collectively have um you
know so it kind of speaks to the idea of
having heterogeneous agents with
heterogenous you know concerns but
nonetheless with an umbrella Collective
concern they're able to accomplish their
goal um this next
one uh rather long title active
inference framework for Collective
parallel problem solving on ink l States
this is a you know I gave this at the
tutorial a couple months ago um I just
recreated uh so I'm this was the point I
was trying to make you can recreate a
lot of these old traditional agent based
models you know using active inference
agents that's what I'm claiming so so
I'm not trying to say oh all of these
traditional models are obsolete uh not
at all I think there's so many
fascinating design principles I would
love one day to recreate the uh the
Santa Fe institute's artificial stock
market but with active inference agents
right we can do that so um so here I
just recreated one where you have agents
who are collectively trying to solve a
problem represented on an Inky landscape
meaning that they're trying to solve a
very complex problem where there are a
lot of interdependencies in different
subparts of the problem you know it's
like uh trying to uh trying to design a
car it's like well you can have a great
car but if you remove the wheels it's no
longer going to really be the kind of
car that you need right or you can
remove the steering wheel right you you
need to have a certain combination of
pieces there to have a proper solution
so agents collectively do that and you
can study like well how well do they do
that do they get stuck you know with a
suboptimal solution uh and then
furthermore you can look at metrics like
oh if we run this in different ways uh
what is the connectedness needed uh to
for them to reach the optimal uh uh
solution or otherwise so and then
finally this is not an active inference
uh paper um but this is this is just a a
reinforcement learning uh you know based
problem but I I included it here because
I just want to make the point that this
is this is focused on industry right
this is focused on multi-agent settings
where you can have them kind of work in
M manufacturing firm that involves like
making a lot of kind of Rapid decisions
in order to uh manufacture particular
products how you could have agents kind
of synchronized in a way that they can
accomplish you know that goal and uh
again similarly with with traditional
agent based modeling where you could you
know swap them out with active inference
agents so to speak might be able to do
this you know take that same approach
with looking at how people are using
reinforcement learning today I think it
lead to very interesting results so I
just again just trying to bridge these
kind of uh you know
dialogues between people so now we'll
move to llms as agents um this I just
think it really needs to be uh addressed
um so llms have been uh increasingly
integrated into a wide array of
potential use cases uh you know I I
included some resources here like there
there just uh you know dozens on dozens
of of research papers that are being
published uh that try to use llms in
these kind of agentic ways where it's as
if an llm is an agent who you know
supposedly makes decisions autonomously
and so on um again they're showing more
and more sophisticated reasoning
capacities um they're they're they're
having uh kind of longer uh context
windows and output Windows meaning you
can feed them even more information at
one time they can release even more or
output even more information at one time
uh you can also upload your own uh text
files documents write your own prompts
for them to respond to so in that qu in
that case if an llm uh really is an
agent then why not just skip all of this
stuff with reinforcement learning with
active inference why not go straight to
using LMS as agents of course I'm gonna
argue like we should not do that that be
um I mean it would it would be
irresponsible at this current moment in
time in terms of llm development I I
would I would argue that that would be
kind of ir responsible unless you're
just kind of making you know some kind
of you know entertaining or or fun app
that uses llms or something but for for
something that that that calls for you
know much more discretion I would not do
that so what what are the biases here um
uh llms are trained on large corpuses of
existing text we all know this uh what
that does is it kind of sediments a
series of cultural scientific
explanatory rhetorical Prejudice
information figuratively the snapshot of
the retrievable Web scrapable Internet
other digitized human and AI produced
text to which uh the lm's internal
parameters which are you know blackbox
parameters now we have llms being
trained to where they have seven plus
billion parameters on the inside um you
know and then consequently the their
outputs are just kind of reflective of
this so so a lot of these uh you know
prej prejudices have been addressed you
know very obvious in a certain way very
unfortunate things that we saw with
initial LMS were like racist you know or
or sexist or otherwise kind of outputs
coming from them based upon the
materials they were trained on people
are trying to find different ways of of
training them differently to to get them
to elicit the responses they uh that we
want but that's the thing what's crucial
when working with LMS is the prompt cell
so I you know I I want to think you know
just put yourself in the chair you know
facing a computer and you're using an
llm what's really going on you as the
user you prompt the llm after it's
already been trained you have your own
purpose or goal in mind that the llm
does not hold for itself quick mention
I'm aware that I'm doing some slideshow
karaoke I just for anyone who's like H
but uh to know there's a lot of
information I want to make sure I cover
it thoroughly uh so so the user must
provide the context for this goal uh or
purpose and their prompts in the hope
the llm will catch on less figuratively
they hope that the llm will be able to
predict the series of words and
sentences which cor respond in the
user's final opinion to the answer the
user needs or wants right and so after
training the LM it can't actually learn
what the user needs it's it's always in
the user's opinion and we'll get more
into that again it's just making the
point The Prompt itself is incredibly
important this is kind of a a simplified
uh ever so slightly exaggerated uh you
know illustration of the kinds of things
I'm talking about so if I go to an llm
and say hi my name is Andrew it says hi
Andrew it now knows my name how can I
help you today uh I I ask it help me
prepare you know I have a certain goal
in mind I tell it help me prepare an
initial draft for a proor of business
model you know for an idea I have uh you
know here are the following details that
should go into that that business mod uh
model then it produces it for
me and today it can even release it as a
text file and so I could click on it
download it great now what happens
whenever our conversation history is
deleted what happens whenever we exceed
the context window that is repeatedly
being sent back to the llm every time I
prompt it um we have context loss so
whenever that happens the llm you know I
say okay now please help me revise the
file please provide the file you
mentioned it does not recall anything
that came prior right what is my name
your name is me which is is a slightly
exaggerated example but it just really
wanted to make the point like it will
use its reasoning where it's capable
right and and and
confabulation uh is is a kind of a
technical word LMS hallucinate in the
sense that they can they can kind of
reason things in a way that they end up
coming up with false information you
know
um we have to be careful about that
right we have to be very cautious about
a lot of these characteristics of LMS
they effectively I mean I would highly
relate it to someone who has interr
Amnesia right is where where you know
someone cannot actually recall what has
happened uh in the recent past and
nothing you tell it actually gets
committed to long-term memory and so
I've kind of crudely used the phrase
like the llms are kind of like Talking
Heads uh you have to repeatedly tell
everything in every prompt and what's
going on when you interact with GPT is
that a lot of this conversational
history is being stored in the site in
some kind of cache and being resent and
you're not seeing that process because
they want it to be a nice user interface
to where you can more easily use it
so recent agentic Frameworks and
workflows abound in recent Recent
research yet the issues presented by
limited context Windows confabulation
Etc still abound lenss with these
conversational histories have been
considered to be age
in various cases yet in order to try and
overcome some of the issues that I
pointed out there are a variety of
Frameworks that are being developed you
know so one idea is an actor critic
framework you could have two or more
agents you give them different role
prompts you tell one of them oh you're a
creative you know scientist and the
other one you say oh you're you know
you're a harsh critic and and expert in
literature on uh this scientific topic
and then you have the first agent try
and innovate and come up with something
and then the the second agent critiques
the former agent you know so you have
this kind of way of like oh in order to
better ground the information that one
of the so-called agents is is creating
you can um you can use another agent to
kind of critique that make it more uh
yeah grounded to reality um another uh
way of doing this is building up
databases of retriev documents that is
you could you could it's it's an attempt
to overcome the limits of context
windows so what you can do is you can
repeatedly query llm and any true
information as well as any information
you provide yourself through your own
documents your own prompts uh you know
any kind of formal documents you want to
submit you could kind of collect these
in some kind of organized database and
you could query that database in a way
that repeatedly send into the context
window here's only the information that
needs to be set right now based on
everything I have and then that database
kind of acts as your ground truth um
that that's a means of doing it it's
it's rather sophisticated there are
different ways of doing that we'll get
to that soon and finally there's a
thinking or reflecting framework I'm
just spending a second on that it's
where you have an llm uh come up with
things but then have it revise its
previous responses U very similar to an
acurate critic framework it's just
you're viewing it as one one so-called
agent doing this as opposed to two um in
all cases the prompts are still
incredibly important so what's in a
prompt well uh there are many people who
have now you know uh coined the phrase
prompt engineering which is at this
point has kind of become a field or even
art in and of itself this is a recent
recent systematic survey prompt
engineering uh that that covers
literally dozens of techniques uh for
anyone who's you know interested in that
um the there are many ways of doing this
furthermore some other problems include
uh difficulties handling numerical or
symbolic problems so intuitively you
know if you read 2 plus 2al 4 is a
string as opposed to being able to
recognize oh these are two numerical
values uh that need to be added be an
addition rule to compute a further value
you know it might not be tokenized
properly um and so that the LM doesn't
actually know how to deal with that
despite the fact that to you it's very
obviously just a mathematical statement
um so llms are getting better at dealing
with math much better actually but they
still risk this kind of in Precision so
if we want to actually incorporate LMS
into software applications especially
those that have Stakes right those that
have real world consequences where
you're actually employing them in any
kind of like in depth industry related
setting in relation to what John was
saying in any kind of ecological setting
uh you know situation where you'd want
to really carefully take of things
verify the information and so on you
need everything to be much more precise
and trackable than uh whenever you
whenever you uh use llms in your
application you could have your
application such as you know if you're
developing this in python or Julia or
otherwise you could have that uh code
actually handle the math which is
something we typically already do um as
well as any kind of like if you're able
to hard code any kind of rules that you
can extract out of the text and actually
consider those to be kind of you know
programmable and then you can have them
in in your program and and have that
logic be carried out outside of the llm
and you can just have the llm handle the
natural language aspects um so kind of
my proposal and this I don't want to
spend too much time on this because
we'll see some diagrams that actually
represent the ideas here but uh you know
I argue that that we should be thinking
about things like pre-structured crops
with what I'll call empty spaces uh for
anyone who uses python is very simple
you just create a bunch of
preconstructed prompts that are
structured in a way that you can
basically Supply uh The Prompt here
you're you don't have to do this word
for word but you're effectively saying
here is what I need here is how I need
it how I need your output to be
structured here are my current you know
thoughts or beliefs of what's going on
give me what I need uh but then make it
an F string to where you can have kind
of these empty spaces in between the
prompt uh to where at any given moment
in time say in an agent-based model you
can send the most recent updated
information through the FST string
literal so it's like you're you have a
really nice prompt that really gets at
what you want the LM to send back to you
but if you want to have this run
algorithmically uh you know in a way
that you let it run autonomously it
needs to be that the information in that
prompt needs to be repeatedly updated
again like like reminding the the person
with anterograde amnesia what's going on
now then an hour later what's going on
then so
on um bringing it back to active
emerance agents we know they change
their minds through perception they act
to change the world they actually have
capacity for learning including online
learning learning in real time you know
updating their internal model parameters
might be liken into synaptic learning or
modulation in the brain uh you know
updating their beliefs about the
relationships between observations and
states the efficacy of their own actions
you know a lot of these other kind of
cognitive
mechanisms that llms lack so uh to bring
it back llms if they were like agents I
would say that they're like agents who
cannot act nor learn they only observe
and infer uh there's been one argument
that they do act it's just they they
don't quite U you know that because they
don't learn anything it doesn't quite
matter and they can't really observe
that outcome of their their action it's
like their action is they output you
know words and sentences and and that
doesn't actually come back and impact
them necessarily in any kind of tangible
long-term way um they are typically
trained once very expensive process some
people have tried to specialize LMS by
only training them predominantly on
medical texts to make a kind of a
medical llm or legal texts for legal llm
you know but still we're stuck in this
like lack of online learning or or or
something like clear
preferences from a neurobiological
perspective LMS have very broad yet
immutable long-term memory and uh you
know they're trained on a lot of
information and then they have a highly
variable short-term memory it's their
context window which if anything happens
to that and it's gone then they've lost
you know all
context um and so I argue that we should
think of uh llms uh you know as as a a
language processing tool I think they're
very effective at that they're they they
absolutely outperform Us in terms of
being able to feed them many many Texs
and then you know quizzing them on those
texts just in a plain as day they far
out you know they exceed us and this
this part of why they're so popular now
uh and being considered for software
applications then from this vantage
point we can Envision
augmenting agents who learn and act such
as active inference agents with
something like the Capac capity for
natural language is how I'm I'm
currently phrasing it so this is kind of
my diagram uh diagrammatic you know
attempt at formalizing this for for
anyone um these are a lot of the design
principles that are going into our
biofirm that we're developing right um I
I started developing this whenever I
considered how could I have an active
inference agent write a scientific paper
by prompting an llm like on its own
right right so so each action of the
agent was you know uh prompt the llm to
find more literature and citations uh
another discret action is uh you know
write or revise your abstract you know
and these other aspects of writing a
paper then seeing if it can kind of you
know choose for itself what to what to
write rewrite update so on and how would
that work and so a lot of that thinking
has kind of gone into this project um in
this case what you would have is you
know for for a user of the biofirm they
would be able to kind of uh you know
submit their own documents PDF text this
is kind of the grounding truth
representative of you know the users own
preferences their goals what it is they
want to accomplish that gets input into
structured prompts you know FST string
literals like the the empty spaces that
way it'll it'll basically take your
inputed information and restructure it
in a way that's needed to get the kind
of answer uh and the kind of response
that you need right so the documents are
sent to structured prompt uh which is
then itself sent to the llm which
processes it and returns your structured
response structured responses uh you
know allows encoding for agent
observations meaning you could in a very
simplistic example you could ask an LM
is this a good idea yes or no
and that can be encoded as a zero or a
one and then the zero or one can then be
you know read up as an observation for a
particular observation modality that
that an agent a PDP is equipped with
right that that's a this very kind of
Elementary approach uh but it's I hope
it maybe explains the idea for for
programmers who who are interested in
these kinds of things um and so uh you
know that observation is then taken in
and and then the agent can infer States
per usual What It Takes the lm's you
know feedback into account it's decision
making and then we have expected free
energy meaning you know um the free
energy it computes condition on its
preferences right so it's like saying oh
the agent can take in an lm's you know
natural language based feedback uh to
the users initial preferences as
elicited and language and the agent can
use that feedback to make decisions in
order to follow through on its own
preferences or goals right so you have
this kind of reciprocal relationship
between um the the user and via the llm
by cariously to the the agent and then
back again as you can uh take the
agent's current internal beliefs you
know it elicited this policy it it now
believes this it previously observed
this those can be put back into a
structured prompt uh which could then
you be sent to an llm for a new
structured response and that might you
know that might be something that
involves like reporting like the agent
is you know in natural language
reporting its beliefs about what's going
on and then that can be useful to the
user and then be sent to uh what we'll
for now call A A Knowledge Graph
apologies they just now realize that
this is being covered um yeah and so
then this knowledge graph and we'll get
more into that I was very happy to hear
some other people making references to
to knowledge graphs uh during the
Symposium um you know it can be done in
different ways but a general sense of a
knowledge graph that this is kind of
like your database of of knowledge that
you're gathering over time in terms of
you know natural language based
knowledge so it's kind of like you're
storing the context of the moment you're
kind of storing the truth you're storing
the history of what's going on in terms
of these agent llm interactions uh you
know and then that way the user has the
means of reviewing for themsel in
everyday terms what has played out
during the course of simulation so
that's kind of the design principle and
then the knowledge graph this is a way
of kind of overcoming The Limited
context window issue so in a general
sense uh and I'll I'll mention I'm you
know a lot of my thinking about the
knowledge graph comes out of this really
like very recent exciting work uh being
done by Marcus J buer uh who works at
MIT right now um you know he's been
trying to find ways of of using llms to
to you know um basically go over many
texts in order to find patterns in the
text that can then be you know kind of
put together almost in this like a
sharian like Innovation Way of like uh
just recombining materials that already
exist in text but maybe humans
themselves have not yet made those
connection themselves of oh uh we know
all of these many different things uh if
we look at it this way that actually
leads to a new innovation that we could
come up with you know uh we we just
didn't make that connection before but
we did now it's like oh you can have
llms who are highly you know
sophisticated whenever it comes to to
going over large amounts of tax having
them make those kinds of discoveries um
so anyway that that's the kind of where
this is coming out of um and then uh
sources for updating the knowledge in
the graph may include user documents
upto-date environment or resource
reports agent beliefs domain knowledge
regarding to your use regarding your use
case llm responses to structured queries
we kind of looked at that before um
business model as a shared narrative it
doesn't have to be a business model but
you know it could be you have many in
the context of the biof firm which we'll
get into shortly um you know the idea is
agents are working for a firm and so
they have this kind of they need to have
this shared narrative between them that
kind of captures all the crucial core
elements uh describing what are the
operations of the firm what are the
guidelines what are things that they
need to attend to uh you know regulatory
or legal standards um what are what what
are the their current financial
statements what resources do they
currently have available uh what are
what are what are the perspectives of
all their different stakeholders you
know being able to synthesize that
information into you know kind of a
singular document that's that's short
enough that it but but nonetheless uh
Rich enough that can be repeatedly sent
back to the llm to remind the llm this
is what we care about these are our
constraints these are our Central
concerns right now or otherwise so
anyway uh I'm getting a little ahead of
myself but it just that's how we can
start to develop a Knowledge Graph
overcoming The Limited context window by
having a graphical structure to the
knowledge you can keep it nicely
organized and uh as we know with graph
structures with having nodes and edges
you can have along the the the edges can
kind of be the descriptors that relate
you know multiple Concepts as nodes
right so you can kind of Traverse this
knowledge graph to make connections
between all the entities within it uh
these are the visuals here actually
Daniel created these based on some
particular LM uh structured prompts that
that he ran and then kind of analyzed
um and so the these kind of principles
are going into it so by using
pre-structured prompts and querying our
knowledge graph um you know we can
repeatedly kind of communicate what is
the situ situational context of what's
going on uh in the moment as well as
here's the knowledge that we've
accumulated so far that can help with
problem solving during the moment this
allows us to filter down only to the
needed information and synthesize it
reducing the final amount of information
uh in this case tokens which also if
you're using the open AI
API to use the most uh recent like
state-of-the-art models where we're
usually spending at least a few pennies
per llm uh uh prompt or well it depends
but the the point is by reducing the
amount of information flow needed you
can keep costs uh significantly lower as
well and then also um kind of uh quickly
overcome that issue potentially
exceeding the the limit of the context
window and I you know I'm I'm I'm
interested in finding different ways of
describing this I'm a particularly a
large fan of Yori basaki a
neuroscientist NYU who does a lot of
work on on neurobiology and and has even
worked with friston at a point in the
past but uh uh so I I included him to
try and give a metaphor of this is this
conceptually can be likened to theories
of episodic memory in the brain uh for
example this this uh one Theory uh that
the hippocampus in the brain is
something like a pointer so whenever you
try to recall you know an episode in in
your life you know that involved uh you
know certain many episodes like in order
to tell a story of what happened
yesterday starting from the morning and
then what did you do uh you know at noon
and what did you do in the afternoon so
on like the hippocampus is a kind of
pointer that that kind of kind of or
almost like a librarian that goes
through
your long-term memory to to kind of pull
out sequentially what's needed in order
for you to tell that story or narrative
in the moment um or from a kind of more
industrial or a modern data analytics
example you could think of this as
querying a database SQL or mongod DB
meaning could be a structured or
unstructured database where a report is
synthesized via joining inquiring only
the necessary tables or catalogs of
blogged information needed for the
report so again it's practical structure
that allows us to kind of more quickly
get the information we need without
having to pull too much more than what
we need um
so now this is example of I'm I'm just
currently phrasing this is like agent
foraging and knowledge updating so it
could be uh starting from the top left
we have our homeostatic agents uh John
made a reference to them earlier um the
sense is that these are agents who have
their own preferences for you know
maintaining their own home stasis they
might be trying to maintain the
homeostasis of their environment in the
case of an agent who designed to take
care of an environment which is what
we'll see in the biofirm uh they'll have
their own current beliefs they're being
updated over time uh you know we saw
kind of an image of the the inner
dynamics of what that looks like for a
PDP earlier they might have their own
goals which again in this case would
probably align with the idea of
maintaining homeostasis you know based
on all of those factors uh that might
lead to you know some pre-structured
prompt leading to something more
specific so in this case this is an
agent who um wants to take care of an
environment uh and this is an agent who
specifically is looking at how to take
care of the soil on a a natural Farm uh
like a land preserver or Farm uh and so
they need more information about the
soil structure so they query they prompt
the llm water causal determinants of
soil structure and Farms you know this
like an initial this is this is whenever
you're first making the knowledge graph
you would want to have this uh this
knowledge at the very beginning of a
simulation right so that it's kind of
building out your knowledge graph to
start so you could ask it this you could
tell it to site your sources or you
could integrate some kind of API uh such
as semantic scholar or other apis try
and check if it's actually pulling from
real citations again we have that risk
of confabulation making up seemingly
true information uh and and so we want
to uh just kind of keep a check on that
so the llm tell you a lot of natural
language based information about soil
structure the determinant different
kinds of manage pra management practices
that could be used to take care of it uh
different kinds of conditions and
relationships between the soil structure
and other aspects of the soil what's
around it all these different things and
then from there we could kind of go back
to the knowledge graph store this
deconstruct this information you know
IDE ideally this would be we'd ask the
llm to structure its output in a
particular way and then we could send
those different aspects of its response
into different areas of our knowledge
graph um so soil structure determinance
management conditions and then also
track the citations the knowledge graph
again it's almost like a
threedimensional structure in that you
could add the time Dimension that is you
could time stamp when all this
information is collected uh as well you
know so it depends on how sophisticated
you want to make your your knowledge
graph this is the last diagram I have
related to this concept but I just want
to include it this is what I mean by um
a structured prompt with empty spaces
right so we have that same agent from
before um now we're sending a structured
prompt I believe this so This Is
pre-structured Right these these these
curly brackets kind of denote like these
are one of the so-called empty spaces I
believe the whatever your current
environment variables are are currently
here's what the agents beliefs are but
our goal is here's our current business
model and our current constraints are
here are current constraints what
Solutions exist to address this this is
incredibly short and simplistic just for
the sake of illustration but the the
idea is you could input you could you
could keep these environment variables
stored in you know your local
environment you know python is storing
and processing them um you know the the
agent beliefs are being extracted from
the agent you could re-encode those with
natural language you know you could you
could you could include information like
oh this agent's belief is representative
of the quality of its environment so
then this gets read as a sentence that's
something like the agent believes with a
you know 02 probability or very low
probability that the current state of is
environment is good you know you could
you could re-encode that so this is
really a conceptual kind of move to try
and find ways Bridging the Gap between
qualitative and quantitative information
uh at no point in my saying that all of
this is the absolute best way to do this
uh what I am saying is that this feels a
little bit like Frontier work uh the
llms are bringing up the question of how
can we properly integrate integrate them
in software applications and I think
these are the kind next steps in terms
of our thinking of of how maybe we
should be approaching this so and then
you can see again uh for the rest of the
the diagram we still have this
communication we can continue updating
our knowledge graph and also pull
information back out of the knowledge
graph to send into the structured prompt
Um this can all be sent to the llm uh
you know and and so the llm could do you
could you could request it to return
your response in multiple ways one way
is you could tell it explain to me a
natural language uh you know what
Solutions exist to address this and then
also ask it in the same move uh you know
also give me uh you know these encodings
of of of your answer so so could be that
that the LM response some kind of
natural language explanation of you know
how to how to handle this problem but
additionally uh here's structured
encoding you requested Den noted as
follows uh a positive one approved
recommendation to carry out available
action six might be the case that this
uh your your agent has an observation
modality meaning it has like a sensory
receptor uh for the llm where a one
corresponds to like an observation level
of like a yes or an approval or you know
go for it basically and then and then
six is kind of like a second observation
modality where the LM tells you which
one of your available actions you should
take so this is just an attempt at
trying to find ways to modify an agent's
architecture such that it has a kind of
receptivity to uh llm outputs uh in a
way that could go from natural language
to actual directives over what to do
given the current context and all the
information you've asked of uh that
you've provided to the LM uh in the
structure
prompt Now we move to the biofirm um so
the biofirm like this is a lot of the
principles I've described this far uh
kind of play into this um again a lot of
work has been done on this by by by
Daniel fredman here in the the talk and
um and then a a lot of initial kind of
coding work was done by myself um and
then we've of course been under Guidance
with Partnership of of John clippinger
as well as David Lovejoy with uh first
principles first uh I really uh like a
lot of kind of the media and writing and
and uh podcasts that they've been doing
and so um I I would strongly suggest
checking them out uh and uh it's been a
pleasure working with them so far and uh
so with the
biofirm we actually we have a
significant amount of code largely built
out uh you know and kind of organized by
Daniel uh with the under the active
inference institute's own GitHub
repository currently in a sub project
biofirm um we also have a whole another
library that we'll look at soon uh but
for now this is kind of the foundational
the starting point of the biofirm tool
highlights right now we're building
active inference agents as a you know
using pmdp which is you know essentially
has been has already been referenced
earlier in the Symposium a kind of Port
of uh of SPM the the mat lab Library
developed by you know friston and others
um and so uh you know it's been a really
good library to to kind of work with and
quickly start trying to implement some
of our ideas the open AI API um many of
you who have worked with LMS and and and
tried to integrate them into code like
are already familiar with this um but
basically it's a way of quickly being
able to prompt within your your coding
environment uh a wide array of llms uh
including the most recent ones and you
know the new chat GPT or llama or
otherwise models claw it and en cursor
which you know this is not necessarily
essential to developing the biofirm but
uh it's just uh Daniel has kind of
opened my eyes so to speak to to the
wonders of of kind of integrating for
developers um being able to have uh an
IDE where you're editing code and then
you can use an llm to help you write
that code and obviously you always want
to go back and look and make sure that
it wrote the code that you actually
intended but uh it it can it can you can
dramatically reduce the number of times
you need to hop into say stack Overflow
for example if that makes sense to to
programers so it's great for
productivity uh and then also some major
things Daniel put out is um these uh
live streams that cover a lot of the
development of the biofirm so far um
both of them are huge I mean we're
looking at a couple hours or so of of
material and we have close direct Code
walkthrough today originally ideally I
might have gone through some kind of
code walk through um one I don't think
we're quite there yet in terms of being
able to to um we can demonstrate the
principles but in order to have
something that's kind of like within the
context of okay we're doing you know the
active Ence Symposium uh and and we kind
of need to keep things streamlined we're
not quite there yet but you can get a
very big picture of what's going on in
that code and and get an actual code
walk through by having a look at these
live streams that that Daniel put
out so the
biofirm excuse me um uh essentially in a
biofirm agents are working in a firm is
like setting the scene uh to maintain
the homeostasis of an environment be a
Farm Natural land preserve and it could
be it could be many things but for now
it's I'm trying to kind of constrain uh
to kind of an example um agents prefer
both in a colloquial sense they want
this but also in a sort of basy and
prior computational sense to observe
themselves maintaining their environment
H stasis their own Survival and health
in this sense are directly linked with
environmental uh survival and health
mapping internal states to inferred
external States meaning their own
internal beliefs are you know they're
trying to model their own beliefs uh
directly as you know kind of these these
proxies for what's going on outside of
them in the environment so they're
they're very directly trying to map
themselves to to their environment all
of that being conditioned on preferences
again what do they prefer
homeostasis right so they they're trying
to model their environment internally
for themselves while simultaneously
trying to keep that environment within
some kind of H homeostatic range we'll
get to a more concrete example what that
means um but for now we can just think
of it as like um you know that an
agent's own homeostasis involves
realizing his preferences relatable to
how humans burn act to maintain their
body temperature oxygen and blood flow
since it's safety security whether it be
physical or or economic um so in this
case minimizing their own uncertainty
condition on preferences maintaining
homeostasis is equivalent to M
minimizing uncertainty about if the
agent is successfully keeping the
environment in a homeostatic State
that's it's kind of a one sentence you
know concise way of looking at that
they're minimizing their certainty about
if they're able to successfully maintain
the environment of homeostatic State uh
from there we uh you know ideally what
we would do is move on to building a
knowledge base for example a kind of
Knowledge Graph uh which itself would in
an initial setup phase would involve uh
User submitted documents uh so for our
example case we actually did submit both
a real document that John supplied uh
related to uh this this Farmland uh kind
of natural Preserve that he himself has
taken care of of course it's been
redacted um but uh the point is that
this gives us a kind of real world
example that we are quite familiar with
uh containing a document that we can use
you know for an initial testing use case
um and then um you can also do other
things you can send in specific kinds of
like structured queries uh you know
asking for more domain knowledge or
information about say how do we take
care of a farmer otherwise and we have
all of that then we follow that up by
yeah structured prompting another idea
we have that I won't go too much into
right now but one idea is that you could
actually extract out of natural language
potentially like sistic reasoning based
rules uh that there's a you know
researcher axle constant who's done some
work uh in the legal domain and looking
at uh kind of basian uh probability and
graphs and relating that to syllogistic
reasoning I think that would be a really
nice way of concisely extracting natural
language rules turning them into
something kind of like symbolic you know
uh objects in Python that can be used as
formula for for doing different kinds of
reasoning that that increases precision
and reduces the need to make so many llm
calls and having the LM do that but it's
a thought um anyway in any case all this
all the whole development of the
knowledge based Knowledge Graph is
motivated by agent preferences and
beliefs um so social science and I don't
want to get too far away from that um
you know I've been talking about a lot
of design principles but I think the
biofirm itself as currently it is an
open source uh you know sort of resour
it's still heavily under development
I'll get back to you know the aspects of
what's going on with that a little bit
later um but but currently there's a lot
of De developing development being made
and is being written in a way that we
ideally in the future would like this to
be adaptable to different circumstances
it might be the case this could be quite
useful actually for continuing social
scientific research the form of an agent
based model um you know you could
consider that these might not
necessarily be agents in a firm you they
might not have a a a business model they
might have something else they might
have you know a constitution uh you know
that that links all of them or otherwise
um for now I'll continue working U
focusing on the biofirm but I just want
that to be born in mind that I don't
want to present this as if it's a highly
specific use case that you know doesn't
go that doesn't generalize you know
allow for generalizing Beyond itself um
but for now we'll stick with with uh
focusing on it um so social science we
have agents who are collaborating in
coalitions of agents and networks of
Agents uh we have you know attempting to
say that we can augment agents with with
natural language State belief reporting
uh with consequent development of a
cultural uh and this is Dr clippinger
view you know if we have agents who are
motivated to take care of land and then
they collect uh knowledge that that
corresponds to that and then they're
using and communicating using this
knowledge you know that then this kind
of becomes something like a culture so
we're looking at something like a kind
of cultural grammar or or set of scripts
that are being developed uh by via these
agents taking care of uh you know the
the the the land around them and and we
have shared narratives and then on top
of that we also you know in a realistic
scenario we would have agents who are
doing economic resource management and
potentially trying to uh you know
generate some kind of value in some kind
of way basically replenishing or
regenerating sources available to
themselves or otherwise and then on
value generation and this comes back to
the very start where I refer to
utility as being kind of like what was
previously the pen penultimate sort of
uh uh incentive for for agents in
traditional agent-based modeling now if
we shift that to where now we're looking
at expected free energy as the thing to
be minimized wise um you know and in
correspondence with kind of the the
principles of act difference then uh
what we're doing is that we're looking
at this is you know like the
approximation of uncertainty condition
on preferences uh agents are trying to
minimize that value where there uh with
value generation a whole another thing
we could do is look at each of the
agents marginal contributions to the
minimization of this quantifiable metric
uh that is uh expected free energy uh
for the whole firm like look at their
marginal contributions to minimizing the
uncertainty of the firm and then that
itself becomes kind of value you know is
we can accumulate that view that is kind
of like uncertainty reduction is what
generates value so that crucially this
accumulation it's not some arbitrary
floating value who whose own value you
know changes based upon kind of Market
speculation Dynamics or otherwise
instead the momentto moment value
generation car that that that occurs
during the course of a simulation of a
biofirm it reflects the agent actual
learning and capacity for taking care of
their environment as proxied by expected
free
energy and then the the kind of broader
multi-agent setting and Future Vision
for the biofirm their cultural aspects
again as I mentioned earlier this kind
of an Ever evolving accumulation of
shared knowledge again we could have
time stamps that also means that we
might need correction of that knowledge
over time um we'll talk about that more
shortly um uh anyway the the evolution
of the knowledge graph it's motivated by
mirrors agents motivated to accomplish
Collective goals for homeostasis from
various perspectives um you know you
might have agents who are specialized in
one way agents in another you might have
multiple stakeholder uh perspectives
that are being fed into that initial
Knowledge Graph or or along the way
during the course of the simulation
uh
ethical uh ideally would um it would
exhibit these kinds of principles like
by accumulating different perspectives
between agents between users
stakeholders uh you know in the case of
Biore Regional modeling where where
there can be very very many people
potentially involved in in looking at uh
or being affected by how an environment
is uh is being is being cared for taken
care of or managed or governed you know
we being able to actually submit these
these potentially conflicting or at
least different uh perspectives from
various stakeholders those could be
submitted to the program could also
include Financial regulatory or
sustainability related knowledge um you
know that can allow for comparing and
synthesizing various perspectives again
in some some kind of after critic
framework you know is I mentioned
earlier like a lot of methods have been
used to try and overcome the issues of
llms and so we be remiss not to to uh
employ those in various ways where
appropriate that way we can better
ensure that the information that's being
used and processed and being fed into
agent decision making and and so on uh
taking care of an actual environment uh
we can make sure that it's much more
accurate coherent also identify faulty
or contentious information if the Agents
come up with a very aggressive policy
you know prior to its implementation
could be critiqued and revised from an
ethical regulatory or legal standpoint
and all this is
collective uh you know we can kind of
synthesize the information I already
touched on this earlier resynthesizing
core information or primary information
in the knowledge graph into being some
kind of summary business model
Constitution set of protocols protocols
or missions that the agents have um and
then uh sustainability Resource
Management um you know making sure that
agents are aware of available resources
uh combined with quantitative analysis
you could you know if you're looking at
a real world setting you'd be looking at
things like price information
forecasting supplies needed for a
particular policy might have qualitative
reasoning involved such as why like
which supplies are needed for a task
what purposes uh within what guidelines
um that's something I've been thinking
about as well for a related Institute
project uh called farmworks uh we might
talk about that later we'll see um and
then heterogeneity agents agents might
be preconfigured or learn they
necessarily will learn over time
assuming we we Implement learning and
their architecture more than likely well
it depends on how and for what purpose
and then they might even you know evolve
so to speak to specializing different
skills knowledge uses allowing for
agents to collaborate under broad
shareed goals while working on subtasks
there's some nice um we were joined by m
yesterday um during the first
Workshop um so has been involved in a
lot of this previous work and then um
you know another reference to kind of
the as well the industrial example that
I gave earlier to how how we might think
about some of these things um basic form
of a homeostatic agent um this is uh
just take a
second homeostatic agent this is the
general just kind of quick natural
Language summary of its its internal
architecture it's it's incredibly
simplistic this is sort of like a sort
of a kernel of what is the initial
formation of a homeostatic agent prior
to any uh additional you know
modification or or changes in its
architecture that you think might be
required for the situation at hand for
now let's say there's a single
environmental variable uh what we did
and um you I'll talk more about it later
but the idea is that we have an
environment that we've an artificial
environment we generated we generated it
based on the documents I mentioned
earlier including John's Farmland
document as well as particular prompts
submitted to the llm to kind of compose
what are the initial makings of our our
knowledge graph and it came up with soil
structure as being one of the essential
uh variables that should be included in
our included in our environment and then
we have an agent here who's kind of
mapping itself trying map itself to this
quantitative value uh it is a question
uh right now of you know I I can imagine
those who do active inference like a
question might be why use a PDP why
would you not use you know a continuous
time continuous State space model uh for
for now we're going with pomdps uh in
part because uh we're assuming that
we'll be using agents to model highly
complex environments where it's not so
simple as to kind of follow uh simple up
or down uh scale or say that the the the
variable is necessarily being defined by
you know some kind of goian uh
distribution and being sampled from it U
it might be the case that this is much
more complex there might be changing
conditions or otherwise and any case for
initial testing environments is also a
rather quick thing to two I will admit
so um but for now uh the idea is that
you'd have a PDP who can view the data
over time at each time step step uh
Daniel ran this one for uh actually I
don't remember if I ran it he probably
did uh over 10,000 times steps um and so
at each time step uh the agent observes
if the current value is above or below
some homeostatic range which the agent
prefers it fly in right and so it infers
the H state of the variable is it
actually if I observe low is it actually
low uh if it's in its homeostatic range
is it actually in its homeostatic range
or is it act in reality is it really
high or otherwise you know and uh the
another question as to whether this is
necessarily a partially observable
environment since this this seem to be
reflective of real data but again this
allows for the space that there might be
very complex relationships between soil
structure and let's say uh um uh
moisture levels in the soil or or mic
Pro bioactivity within the soil or or
other kinds of things that that that
really matter here to where it's much
more complex than just being able to say
oh just because this went low that means
I need to try and bring it back up as
much as possible really fast right so uh
there might be more nuance and having
more sophisticated architectures might
be able to to kind of parse through that
problem including increasing uh
inference Horizons or or including more
other variables that it tries to map um
and in actions the agent can increase
maintain or decrease the variable uh
right so again very simple a little more
details later on on how that can how
that can work but just say
straightforward it's kind of like the
agent is trying to balance out this
metric um given that a lot of it all of
its
fluctuations uh aside from the agents
actions impacting it are coming from its
relationship with all the other
environmental VAR in its ecosystem so
it's kind of like the agent is trying to
map its internal understanding of what's
going on with the environment's behavior
and then the agent of course prefers to
see this within its homeostatic range
and so it will choose actions that it
believes will help this variable to get
back into its homeostatic range so from
there we can view this like as a whole
ecosystem of variables
so this this kind of defines our
environment that we're looking at right
in agent based modeling setting we have
our homeostatic agents and then we have
our entire environment composed of all
these environmental variables and over
in a real world setting whether you're
running a firm a farm or otherwise you
know each of these variables could be
mapped to you know an iot device uh they
could be mapped to you know some kind of
uh uh logged uh observations you know
that your team makes as to what's going
on with the farm right now um I guess
I'll bring up Farm works again briefly
we've been looking at a lot of farm uh
data lately that's been collected by
farmers and getting some inspiration on
how they go about doing those things but
I will say that this uh this environment
that we have here is entirely
artificially generated based upon
inspiration from text um so if we think
about this as something like agents are
trying to solve a non-equilibrium steady
state uh what is that mean I I'll try
and summarize by saying that we're
trying to maintain the structure and
properties of the farm what is it that
makes a farm a farm well if your soil
moisture Falls dramatically too low and
then suddenly all the organic matter and
it dies and then many of these other
things start to fall apart well now
we're not quite looking at at at at
homeostatic uh soil anymore right so we
kind of have like this this natural
decay or dilapidation of of the system
the ecosystem and so agents are having
to repeat like
continuously uh you know kind of
actively maintain uh through control
inputs meaning through their actions uh
they're trying to keep these variables
within homeostasis and these it's worth
noting these these Target ranges
homeostatic ranges might change
themselves over time right due to uh you
know we can imagine um the the target
soil temperature range might change to
to adjust for you know seasonal crop
change um it also might also account for
certain kinds of like exogenous or
external shocks to the system the impact
of climate change there might be a
natural disaster that occurs or
otherwise that itself can really change
the Dynamics required to attempt to
maintain the EOS system uh as it is or
as it was or if it needs to kind of
change in order to continue
existing given uh what kind of shock
occurred so to maintain these desired
homeostatic States the agent must uh
continuously work against yeah these
these natural tendencies towards
dilapidation States I've already
mentioned this many times these these
states these envir uh variables may have
complex interdependent relationships may
call for agents with forward-looking
inference Horizons um you know of course
if we over maintain the soil uh you know
put too many product in it or or do
other things that might still be okay
for the crops it might harm local
biodiversity uh you know local animals
accidentally cons you know consuming
different kinds of uh um um you know
materials that were that were used to
take care of the soil and suddenly they
die that harms local biodiversity and
yet uh biodiversity might also include
uh pests in the environment that
themselves then harm the soil or crop
growth so it's just um being able to
kind of adjust to all of these highly
complex variables and crucially in
reality we might only be able to impact
some variables second some variables and
not others thus agents might specialize
in handling one particular controllable
variable and study its relationship with
the other variables leading to
actionable predictive planning another
kind of everyday explanation of this is
like um you know I I mentioned I'm a
data analyst I work in education and so
um you know I'm I'm frequent looking at
a lot of data regarding um um students
and kind of our institution and so on
I'm based in Chicago uh some things that
we can change our bus routes for our
students to make sure that they can get
to school safely uh something we cannot
control is the amount of crime in
Chicago which um anyone in the US knows
is a that would be very difficult to do
right so so so we're looking at there
are all kinds of factors in our
environment that we cannot control and
then there's what we can and then trying
to find can we control what we can
control in ways that kind of can balance
out with all these things that we cannot
control right so that is very crucial to
be able to identify and then measure
analyze those kinds of relationships
whenever we're trying to design any kind
of concrete actionable uh uh policy
right or intervention that you might
want to
make and then uh John referenced the
commons earlier right and Elanor
ostrom's work
um homeostatic agents solving
non-equilibrium stud States the ever
ever solving the commons so so I'm I'm
trying you know I I was thinking about a
lot of these principles and ostram was
required reading for me as someone's
coming you know from a social sciences
background and so I this part of why I
find this project so interesting and why
I find it fascinating to try to realize
a lot of these things um in principles
involved so we we have rules conditions
adaptation I mean the agents necessarily
have to adapt to the environment around
them if you provide some kind of Kernel
agent and and give it some space to
figure out what it is it needs to do
it's necessarily going to have to adapt
right so so we have that attention
towards the local um recognizing
uncertainty and adaptation you know
agents will have to take care of
homeostasis manage resources through
learning uh to to change conditions and
broader unobserved uncontrollable
environment in the sense of um you know
there are many things going on that the
agents cannot directly observe um there
are other things that will occur that
were unexpected you know so and then
also there might be relationships within
the variables themselves that you know
for example there might be some kind of
critical threshold that's hit by one
variable that then has some kind of
domino or Cascade effect on the others
you know so that that's why I include
both the phrases endogenous or exogenous
shots um you know being able to to watch
out for those kinds of Dynamics then
governing the commons you know that's
sort of that's sort of the benefit uh of
you know if if it can be done right if
it can be done successfully integrating
llms in you know a
very in a very thoroughly considered way
that allows for you know accurate
information uh uh uh accumulation and
sharing and then using it for
implementing policies um you know that
that's the aspect that kind of keeps
things grounded and then and then gives
this kind of natural language based way
of dealing with an environment you know
this this kind of just repeats many
things I mentioned before but we're
synthesizing a lot of info from various
stakeholders uh various domains you know
that are needed to handle the problem
repeatedly grounding agents of common
goals from maintaining the environment
against perturbation capture maintaining
its Markov blanket and then nested
collaboration potentially so just as
users can practice oversight by running
these models um agents themselves you
know you might have agents who are at
another layer so to speak who who
maintain their own oversight over other
agents or coalitions of agents and those
uh those kind of hierarchical Agents
might themselves act as something like
an observer role um they might recognize
a broader issue going on
uh in The Firm that isn't being
accounted for by specialized agents and
so you can have those kinds of kind of
hierarchical uh uh specialized uh
structural roles um that that allows for
this kind of nested uh nestedness and
how the environment is maintained um you
know and and then it's a very
interesting idea that I was going to
bring up later but in the context of
like looking at Biore Regional hubs or
something along that line I mean if you
were actually employing something like a
biofirm to a real world scenario that I
don't see any reason why you couldn't
have some way of interfacing between
different biof firms right because if
they're actually playing out in reality
and building their own knowledge graphs
you know say in real time and some kind
of way then then you could very much
have that kind of interfac and you could
have you know structured prompts pulling
from the knowledge graph of one biofirm
you know sending that information to
another biofirm and back uh you know so
so that's you know I I don't want to get
ahead of ourselves but because the vast
majority of the actual concrete work
that's been done on the biofirm has only
been over the course of frankly the past
couple of weeks I mean longer than that
for sure in terms of of John developing
the ideas conversations we've had over
the past couple months but whenever it
comes to developing this stuff and
actually realizing it it's it's still
quite new so it's very exciting to to
report biofirm for users let me just do
a wrap okay
um I'm gonna have yeah yeah I'll speed
this up a little bit um biofirm fre
users yeah uh one you know for for for
for a user's perspective first you
submit your documents as I've mentioned
many times uh you know your own PDFs
real world information uh you know if if
you want to submit textbooks you know
regarding uh agricultural techniques and
methods for taking care of farms you
know including formula that describe
relationships something you could have
from there the direction is to have
there are two intended kind of potential
paths you could take right now all the
testing is being done with the first
path but the ideal is to move it in the
direction where you could have both
available first one is uh for being able
to explore counterfactual so we generate
synthetic data using domain knowledge or
historical data that's what we're
already doing and then second direct
application that would be where you're
actually able to send in data and have
it being streamed and have this play out
real time this very much you know kind
of in the future but that it's sort of
on the roadmap so to speak um and then
once you followed one of those paths uh
you could generate an environment for
your agents and then also you could
construct applicable agents meaning
agents to your design or ones that kind
of fit the situation or be mapped
particular environmental variables as we
saw with the agent who takes care of the
soil structure earlier using agent maker
uh which is kind of a entire addition
that that that d you kind of Zoom
through uh being able to incorporate
included there's more information on
that uh the second live stream that was
released um from there you would uh
simulate uh your agent based model
meaning there would be an initial uh
setup phase that takes in your initial
documents and so on constructs the
agents constructs the artificial
environment then runs your action
perception Loop it keeps things moving
data and llm responses are encoded as
observations for agents agents take
these observations take care of their
environment so we already know
homeostasis for the agent based on how
it setup is kind of hardcoded into its
design and Ma to the home homeostasis of
its environment and finally there would
be obviously we would want this
analytics so having some kind of
analytic Suites that allows you to
derive insights from different kinds of
metrics that are being recorded over
time there might be different kinds of
like llm summary reports and
recommendations that actually distracts
the metrics and you know through a
pre-structured prompt as I've said a
million times during the course of this
you know using prur prompt can in put a
lot of these results and then and then
have an llm kind of put it into a
natural language like just explain for
you in everyday words here's what
happened here's what's going on here
what the agents believe and so on uh
Biore Regional modeling I wanted to look
at this really
quickly this
is uh a lot of Daniel's work
on uh I mean this is just an initial
step but what's happened is that Daniel
sent particular kinds of structured
prompts you find more information on
this in the first live stream uh but
basically asked about information uh in
very particular ways um to llms and and
did it programmatically was able to
extract incredible amount of information
about these different regions different
counties and uh he started with
California and then moved to to New
England and then it's expanded from
there and so we have like Maine and
Massachusetts so for example uh
Massachusetts uh Hampshire County like
you can uh he sent in like you know
generate some kind of uh Supply
strategist statement um we have copies
of these this is a Json form meaning
it's kind of a set up in a way that can
be read by the
program then here's just a more readable
legible you know every day for a user
report it's like here is you know your
supply chain strategist report on the
ecosystem of that County uh references
to what's going on in terms of its
biodiversity how climate change is
impacting it how land is used habitat
fragmentation water quality so just a
lot of the different things that are
going on specific to each of these
counties you can do that from an AR a
market analyst perspective as as well
try and consider different kind of
opportunities there the current economic
landscape what kind of regulatory
environment compliance requirements are
their state federal local of course
these are currently very short
descriptions uh ideally over time you
would build out your knowledge graph
your your knowledge base you'd actually
you know kind of zoom into each of these
send more follow-up prompts like tell me
more about this you know site your site
the information you're pulling from um
and then you could even consolidate that
so this is this kind of a Consolidated
uh report you know very long for all of
these different Market analyst
perspective an ecological perspective
supply chain strategist and just kind of
finding ways to to synthesize a lot of
um information in one move this was a
business case and I just wanted to show
quickly like here are you know ideas of
you know here you know defining out
potential revenue streams risk
assessment mitigation strategies you
know so it's very in fiveyear financial
projections of course we could pull this
kind of logic back into the program have
local computations done that actually
comes up with much more uh uh uh uh uh
grounded realistic and precise
information based on available resources
that you have or that that at least
artificially the agents have if you're
doing more of an artificial setting um
so yeah it's just it's making all these
linkages so um you know that that
becomes sort of the basis the the
starting point for for our um for the
biofirm so we we then you know again we
generated this artificial environment
all we did was send in user documents
structured prompts through an llm you a
structured response um let me
quickly
yeah um this allowed programming our
environment uh it's it's Dynamics
configuration generating descriptions
for each of the variables they get
stored in this nice Json structured file
ecosystem config you know so I mean we
it you you saw previously like I was
looking in a GitHub repository we like
we were really building out the code in
that in that base um and so anyway that
sticking back to the artificial
environment here this allows us to pull
out yeah what are our variables or
proxies for VAR Ables such indices like
it can be quite difficult to measure
biodiversity so we make an index for
that there might be other ways of doing
that there might be more specific ways
of doing that that fits your own use
case or otherwise we could you know Tor
that um domain inspired quantitative
relationships between the variables you
can even you know with more manual
control you can set the noise levels for
each of these like if you assume that
there might be some noisy process you
know uh from a more mathematical or
statistical perspective how what which
of these are actually controllable or
not for those which are controllable how
much are they controllable can you
dramatically change biodiversity in one
move probably not um or you could and I
don't want to follow that thought
further biofirm development performance
benchmarking uh this is another crucial
part of the biofirm development being
able to actually Benchmark how our
active inference agents uh uh perform
relative to you know some kind of
benchmark Baseline so just having a more
reactive or random sort of thermostat
style like reactive um control so
basically on the left we don't have
active inference agents it's just trying
Instead This is a a more basic uh uh
control strategy that kind of just
reacts to the data it's seeing uh and of
course the data is getting very out of
hand I'm not saying it's not getting out
of hand with the active inference agent
but much more so that's what we're
seeing from initial test case and this
active inference agent on the right is
still that basic kernel homeostatic
agent right it is keeping its Target
within range you know 21% of the time
relative to the random strategy which is
only seven um you know the next steps
would be to actually fine-tune and
modify uh the agents to better match the
situation so far it's it's it's very
simplistic it's only looking at one
variable only tracking one variable has
it's currently not taking in any
information from an llm it's currently
not taking in any information about the
other environmental variables um this
was really interesting to see though
that it already has this capacity for
kind of
outperforming the the reactive model now
we've had some instances where the
active inference agent doesn't uh you
know it maybe matches the reactive model
so it's just you know it's prime time to
to step up the agent development game
you know so that this was just step one
it's like can we can we build it you
know we yes we can so now let's improve
it um analytic Suite we can look at you
know the the variables themselves their
correlations with one another we track
the metrics about the environment over
time then compare how the environment
behaved in different different
simulation settings um you know all
that's what we want to do with
agent-based modeling in the first place
typically we want to be able to run
simulations look at the outcomes based
on different circumstances
and then we can compare you know how
this went using different agents um and
uh you know uh we could use llm
integration to to to translate this into
like a a more readable report for users
um this is a whole another aspect I I
really wanted to emphasize it I I've
made this kind of as an additional
module so it can be edited kind of after
the fact like outside of the main
program uh which which also means that
you know you could you can modify this
fit as you want but basically the idea
is you try and measure the surprise or
uncertainty or expected free energy or
otherwise of the environment here um and
and um basically look at how the actual
variable diverges from where you want it
to be you know the difference uh you
know it's of course it's mathematical
and strong from active inference and
other areas basing in statistics and
mechanics but um the idea is you can
measure how far away it is from where
you wanted it to be in terms of
surprisal uh you know actually capturing
kind of this more rich or nuanced
information about how that variable
moves versus where you want it to be um
and then you can kind of flip that say
oh well in a non-equilibrium steady
state system where more usually than not
the system is going to have a tendency
towards generate uh generating more and
more surprisal that is the the the
complex um relationships between the
variables is going to lead to things
typically going off course Very quickly
if you don't touch them um then in that
case any move at reducing surprise
meaning any move at combating that
natural tendency towards kind of like
chaos or entropy uh you know can be
viewed as a form of generating value and
so this is a kind of additional metric
we could add saying that there's a kind
of value added to having these agents uh
minimizing the surprise meaning
minimizing the free energy meaning
minimizing the distance between
homeostasis and where the data is now uh
right so so we could see that kind of
accumulation over time and again it's
modularized meaning for a user they
could potentially experiment as they
like they could change how this value
added is computed I think that'd be very
interested interesting for people who
are interested in economic
simulations or or doing this you know
differently or want to see like how how
does this work you know um then also
shle value analysis we have shly values
so um in the course of you know these
simulations we have agents trying to
solve or take care of their environment
and so in the case of U shle value
computation what it's doing is that we
can compare how do certain coalitions of
Agents run through the simulation
compared to one another uh in terms of U
you know these different metrics and so
you can see like oh agent all five
agents together uh you know did did
better at maintaining their environment
in
homeostasis uh they they did better than
only having um you know these this other
particular Coalition of Agents but they
actually did worse altogether versus
when you only had these two agents
working together right so it's it's a
very kind of sophisticated way of
looking at how agents are actually
solving the problems and actually
carrying out actions that they need to
carry out um and we can do this you know
for different metrics and we can view
that as you know that that can be
another way of saying this is how value
is being generated from by these agents
right so being able to make those kinds
of you know those kinds of analytics
then uh final yeah these are the last
couple slides GNN and agent maker um
this is very cold it's kind of like uh
you know we did so much rapid
development of the biofirm over the past
couple weeks that this just kind of like
hit me I was like oh I don't I didn't
really think about that but Daniel has
incorporated along with his co-authored
work with Yak smel know in the past um
they've worked on what's called General
notation
notation and and and it's a it's a way
of kind of translating active inference
uh active inference agents meaning
models or architectures uh between
different programming languages
including the able to
being able to compose them using natural
language uh and then also being able to
visualize them graphically like that's
you know it's not quite there yet the
kind of makings for um being able to
have this kind of translatability like
uh you know the ideal would be being
able to write to an llm like hey make an
agent for me that can do this and this
and then by giving the LM certain kinds
of contacts it can fill in the matrices
and and so on as you need it of course
we're still a distance from that but
it's kind of building the framework
towards moving towards that and that way
you can make agents who are much more
tailored to the situation and
furthermore ideally you'd be able to uh
translate them between programming
languages meaning you know being able to
switch your applications in Python or
Julia or otherwise um being able to have
that done for you and then uh Daniel has
basically forked uh the
PDP repository and then built agent
maker on top of it so right now it's
kind of tailored to
PDP um but it could be used in other
ways as well and so we already have some
next steps on the kinds of Agents we
want to make for me it's agents who
should be able to observe the whole
environment but only be able to control
their own respective part to me that's
what would make the idea of like having
a shared common goal amongst
heterogeneous specialized agents like
that's what would real
that so that's kind of the broader view
of the biofirm you start with
inputting your documents your texts your
PDFs uh data for fitting not act um
excuse me that's optional right now uh
it would be more ideal for a real world
setting but for now just generating an
artificial environment just the text is
fine we've been able to accomplish that
so
far and then from there you could fit
agents to the situation or at least
maybe customize them yourself using
agent maker you have the the start of
the your knowledge graph or base being
developed and you have that uh
ecosystem all of its Dynamics and
configuration kind of Spun up then after
that you just run the simulation uh
looking at you know analytics uh we want
to move towards having an interface in
future having dashboards we've already
seen a lot of these um graphs earlier so
it's you know and then we'd also want to
have llns that could actually for the
results and this is basically towards an
adaptable kernel of a biofirm this is
kind of the bigger picture we have
different kinds of design
considerations uh couple highlights we
what we're looking at things like
implementing potentially amortized
inference we're kind of accelerating the
inference
process um using continuous State space
predictions and models you know and then
considering you know we we have an RX
and fur group
at The Institute so we'd like to
potentially move towards moving using a
more reactive framework using RX INF fur
the Julia Library as well as kind of
complimentary uh library for
environments um the ARs environments
Library uh plenty of different ways you
might be able to use different kinds of
apis or Integrations with other
tools um locally storing LMS to mitigate
the issue of having to necessarily like
uh use the open API uh open AI LM API um
so and then obviously integrating you
know key aspects are like the resource
management right and that that's that's
actually I would argue is going to be
one of the easier parts of incorporating
because it's like just as we can
currently read real data or gener
generate artificial data and have the
agents manage that like soil structure
we could do that similarly for different
kinds of like U you know Financial
resource uh values or managing an
account something along those lines
right so bringing it back biofirm
development testing is just a slide I
showed earlier but it's it's just a you
know reinforce here some of the tools we
use some things we want to do in the
future some related Institute projects
related to you know we're working on
projects that relate to mitigating
future existential risk we've applied to
a grant with Forest site there's the fli
grant project farmworks ARX and fur
group there's a a new economic
simulations Related Group some people
are interested in looking at things like
you know simulating currencies and and
so on um in in agent based modeling then
those live stream updates um my
computers having uh repeatedly deciding
to cover things St and that's it so uh
we we went much further on time intended
there was a lot to there was a lot to
cover um really appreciate every
everyone's attention though
um and you know in these 11 minutes we
have left you know if you guys want to
give anything a shot please go for
it voice is going
out no take take some
questions
yeah anyone in the live chat can write a
question John where where does this take
you
Andor what will you plan to do
tomorrow well I think what we tried to
lay the foundation here in a very
thorough way is oh what is a biofirm and
uh and what how is able to address uh
many of the issues that you see and in
people trying to work out a bio uh biof
Financial to the Biore Regional
economics and create the proper
incentives and so um I think what we're
trying to do here is really show that
there's a number I started to say here
are some of the criteria that we're
looking for in particular building with
eler aam and the whole idea of how to
govern a commment is a profound issue
that seem to be intractable to a lot of
people um I think this in my my view
this provides a framework for doing a
scalable framework for doing it a way
involving people a way of applying
scientific methods and creating finan
cial incentives and automating a lot of
the the data collection analysis task
and how you can agents can build up
their own competencies of over the
period of time so there's a lot here
there's a lot to digest um and it does
recommend it does provide a new metric
of value that's based upon and and a
you're not you're not establishing value
the classic economics that our price
Arbitrage or information asymmetry
Arbitrage you're actually saying there's
such a thing as a free energy principle
a scientific process and we can show how
the value is created and then how to
allocate it to those people or those
agents that are creating it so this is
really sort of foundational so we want
to take it in next steps um and what
we're going to be doing tomorrow is is
um actually there's a group of people
who are experts in the sense that they
work with uh how to take multi-agent
architectures and apply them to in some
cases the to the Enterprise from Del
that's doing that another group uh Simon
uh uh Torrance is doing it in terms of
AI looking at framework for agenda
architectures uh there are others are
looking at it applying to the bio uh
Finance bio Regional Finance issues um
so we have that Susanna Choy we also
have uh uh we have Matt who's head
of sustainable finance and metabolic and
then there's John Havens who's been
involved with i e establishing ethical
Frameworks for that application of
geospatial models in AI so it's quite a
combination of people but what we want
them to to look at is what's the impact
of this when you're having fully
autonomous biomedic based agents uh and
what happens when you can apply them not
just to the biometric to the Biore
Regional Finance but also the new notion
of a firm um and I think there's is a
real profound issue here what happens
when you really have autonomous agents
and you create institutions we create
institutions that are supposed to be
above people but the problem is people
populate institutions and they come
captured but what happens if we start to
put these agents and build institutions
that are that are function this way that
are verifiable this way and what does
that happen to what we think about
employment jobs and I mean there's some
really substantive issues here um and
how do you create this as a a public
resource a public good that doesn't get
captured by particularly small interests
so it's a bondad spectrum of questions
we're putting out there um that I don't
think that the public in general fully
appreciates the the the capacity and the
power of an active INF free energy
Principle as applied to economic and and
and societal issues so that's we're
going to try to tackle those issues and
get people talking about it and this is
this is a beginning but we want to take
it next steps and really get rep
reference get actual reference
Technologies out there that we can
actually show and demonstrate and may be
able to
replicate that's that's the the goal
yeah and very helpful I gotta say you
know Daniel kudos to you from all along
I mean both you guys and Daniel just
you've done remarkable work and and and
accelerating this process and we're very
very grateful for that and what active
infes institute there's other things the
other sessions I saw here that seem to
be very relevant to what we're doing so
I'm really looking forward to
collaborating I'm I'm quite fascinated
with with thought Forge with Matt Brown
is doing and doing you homeostatic
networks and it goes back to Ashby and
the law of re a variety I think all
that's applicable to this too so there's
this wonderful synthesis that you've
enabled you you really have I and and
through a singular effort so again
extremely grateful for this
thank you it's been awesome and and
uh lot more I can say but what what what
can we're gonna we're gonna ask more of
you you're I'm not done yet you're not
done no no we we're no the the part that
resonated with me in the presentation
over the last two days of biofirm and
how Andrew laid out all these pieces
pieces is like on one hand we have that
researcher lens again about similarities
and differences and about treating it
like it's an engineering problem and
then I think John you've brought in the
deeper history of Commons and
cybernetics and these more open-ended
problems about how do we connect any
technical
capacity to the
embodiment and the co- enactment of
systems that are livable and
regenerative and that's a little bit of
a different kind of
topic that's one though that that uh
mass convening and
awareness can
[Music]
can fertilize and make
real in a way where the technical
understanding it's like you can read it
for 20 years it's like it is just going
to be the textbook it's just going to be
H something to jump off of and take into
another way it's not like some of these
questions about how different regions
will work it's not it's not in the 2022
textbook so that's applying active
inference is taking the high road and
the low road and variational free energy
expected free energy like all of those
formalisms and then like surprise
surprise
applying them to what matters and
figuring out that project and
operational part and there's just like
there's so many pieces was just like
thinking of the yarn connecting the the
the needs to what we do and don't have
at different levels of Readiness that
takes us back to the tech tree and all
these other ways that we've discussed
coordinating
around that balanced way to think about
Regional and what is Federated what is
transferable how do we deal with all of
these aspects and it's um been a great
journey over the last few months
also well thank you I I what I what I
find so reassuring is that and and you
you see applying the method and then it
starts to explain and you keep applying
it and so it it it doesn't it doesn't
Fade Out it you're not you're not get o
h it doesn't become ad Haw and so I feel
like we're doing something really
principle that is extensible and when I
come from the the the bof finance
community and see all the things that
they've been trying to do are in the
Commons Community say actuallyit there's
a wonderful fit here and getting these
two worlds together is is is is really
important it's a challenge too um but i
i i people want to do that and and
they're looking for something like this
and so I really hope that we could going
to be able to create that marriage as it
were to add one comment on that I think
when you opened today and said well we
could make things fungible we can
connect but that is also part of
replicating if not elaborating the
problem which is the fungibility of
drinking water here and this caler here
and this unique species
here this facilitating that
fungibility is facilitating the capture
of the underlying resource so even if it
were somehow trivial to make like
assertions about
impact
monetized and the whole hypers certs and
impact certification even if that were
trivial and we can just assume that that
we have full observability or something
like that it could even
accelerate Financial capital
based
Cascades and so what what can be an
escape grounding to that and that's
where seeing like whoa the models on
through the Paradigm of incentives are
maximalist and reward
oriented can they be homeostatic or
allostatic oriented to satisfies and be
on paths that bounce
surprise rather than try to maximize but
then as soon as we look around the world
there's things that don't make sense
we're not trying to maximize or minimize
like the
reservoir but rather within a
range and so there's so many things
where we can just
connect first principles of intelligence
and research questions to just like the
calm subtle sometimes ways that that the
technology because to to to move too
fast also would would again replicate
fallacies
right okay
well good luck with the session tomorrow
okay and and I I hope many
people come join and and engage in these
Fun open source meaningful
projects this is just the beginning it's
just a
checkpoint and and uh it's a strong one
and and I'm very pleased with it yeah
cool all right thank you fellas see you
later
guys for